Finding aid for the Barbara Aziz broadcasts collection
Bentley Historical Library
- Interviews and related material, 1988-2013; undated
  - circa March 2005, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:13:10); (Rachida Mohammedi comments on women's history, international view Interviewee/Author/Reader: Rachida Mohammedi, Algerian poet. Topics: Women's History, Arab, Middle East .)
  - circa September 4, 2005, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:53); (Al-Aboudi discusses nuclear contamination following French tests in south Algeria Interviewee/Author/Reader: Khadem Al-Aboudi prof of physics, U. Oran, Algeria. Topics: Algeria, French occupation, nuclear tests.)
    (Translated to English from Arabic)
  - 2006, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:09:14); (Clips edited to document a local NY community festival Interviewee/Author/Reader: Brooklyn community members. Topics: Arab American.)
  - 2007, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:26:22); (Marian Haddad speaks about her work as a poet and literary advisor and her family Interviewee/Author/Reader: Marion Haddad, TX-based poet, literary, consultant. Topics: Arab American literature, poetry.)
  - 2008, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:51:59); (Rezk talks about her aims and experience as a radio host of 2 programs in Algerian desert city of ElOued and its social implications for women Interviewee/Author/Reader: Algerian radio host Baya Rezk (unedited in Arabic). Topics: Algeria, media, Muslim women.)
  - circa 2008, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:32:18); (Edward Said lecture on "The Clash of Civilizations" Interviewee/Author/Reader: Edward Said, Columbia U. Prof. Topics: Edward Said, Global policy.)
  - 2008, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:24:33); (Al-Araji talks about his ambition, economic growth, his country, translated form Arabic Interviewee/Author/Reader: Ahmed Al-Araji, Algerian businessman. Topics: Algeria, economy, history, politics.)
  - 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:43:31); (Hassan Sohbi critiques the French diplomat Alex Tocqueville, author on the racist background to his famous study of USA Interviewee/Author/Reader: Hassan Sohbi, Algerian professor of history, Univ Oran. Topics: Algeria, French occupation, Alex Tocqueville.)
    (Predominantly in French)
  - 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:37:42); (Al-Shaykh, Beirut-based author visiting NY speaks about lastest novel "The Bird and the Locust" Interviewee/Author/Reader: Hanan Al-Shaykh, Beirut based, author. Topics: Arab literature, women, memoir.)
  - circa 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:51); (Philip Kai interviews Shadia Mansour (vocalist) about her music, conditions in Palestine, her identity, global message Interviewee/Author/Reader: Shadia Mansour, Palestinian London-based singer. Topics: Palestine, HipHop.)
  - circa 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:08:55); ("Obama" by author, Abbas Jijan, Iraqi poet, Baghdad Interviewee/Author/Reader: Abbas Jijan, Iraqi poet, Baghdad. Topics: poetry, Arabic.)
  - circa November 2009, (Al-Askari discusses the Five Pillars of Islam)
    - November 14, 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:08:36); (Part 1 of 2. Interviewee/Author/Reader: Saleh Al-Askari, NJ-based Muslim commentator. Topics: Islam.)
    - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:41:31); (Part 2 of 2. Interviewee/Author/Reader: Salah Al-Askari, NJ resident, scholar. Topics: Islam.)
  - December 11, 2009, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:31); (Khaled el-Haggar on his films, interviewed at 17th African Diaspora Film Festival in NY Interviewee/Author/Reader: Khaled El-Haggar Egyptian director, latest film "Stolen Kisses". Topics: Egypt, art, film, Middle East.)
  - 2010, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:25:40); (Malaika interviews Hafez Naziri in NY, about his career, his work and Iranian music, with excerpts of his vocals Interviewee/Author/Reader: Iranian vocalist Hafez Naziri. Topics: music, vocal, Iran.)
  - 2010, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:09:41); (Ismail Khalidi speaks about his current play "Tennis in Nablus", and prospects for Arab American arts in US culture Interviewee/Author/Reader: Ismail Khalidi, NY-based poet, playwright. Topics: Arab Amercian literature, Palestine.)
  - circa 2010, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:26:57); (Iranian director Ghobadi, in NYC for release of "No One Knows About Persian Cats," speaks about directing his various films Interviewee/Author/Reader: Bahman Ghobadi, Tehran-based Iranian filmmaker. Topics: Iran, film, "Time for Drunken Horses", "Marooned in Iraq".)
    (Partially in Iranian)
  - 2011, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:25:06); (Dawn Elder speaks about her early career, founding the International Friendship Festivals, and current Sudan music fest in New York Interviewee/Author/Reader: Dawn Elder, musician, world music publicist, promoter, LA-based. Topics: Middle East, music, Sudan.)
  - 2013, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:21:00); (Aziz interviews Rolla Nashef, director of "Detroit Unleaded" in NYC at the film\'s New York release Interviewee/Author/Reader: Rolla Nashef, Detroit-based filmmaker. Topics: Arab American, film.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:21:53); (Sousa discusses the research work and publications of her engineer father, Ahmed Interviewee/Author/Reader: Alyia Sousa, Baghdad-based author, Ahmed Sousa, Iraqi scholar and author. Topics: Iraq, History ,intellectual.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:19:09); (Aziz interviews Iranian virtuoso Kayhan Kalhor in NY)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:02:34); (Andrea Assaf recites her poem "The Robin Monologues" Interviewee/Author/Reader: Andrea Assaf, US-based performer, poet. Topics: art, theater.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:11:40); (Naomi Shihab Nye poetry recitations Interviewee/Author/Reader: Naomi Shihab Nye, poet. Topics: Poetry, Middle East.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:23:26); (Poems read by authors Naomi Shihab Nye, Khaled Mattawa, Suheir Hammad, Lisa Mohammed Interviewee/Author/Reader: poets Naomi S Nye, Khaled Mattawa, Suheir Hammad, Lisa Mohammed. Topics: Arab American literature, poetry.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:58:00); (A collection of studio readings by Arab and Muslim poets Interviewee/Author/Reader: a collection of studio readings by Arab and Muslim poets. Topics: Muslim, Arab American literature, poetry.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:14:04); (Mahmoud Darwish reciting his work at a public event, location unknown Interviewee/Author/Reader: Mahmoud Darwish, Palestinian, poet. Topics: poetry, Arabic literature.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:06:23); ("Les Odalisque", poem, read by author Mohja Kahf Interviewee/Author/Reader: Mohja Kahf, Poet, Professor of English, U. Arkansas. Topics: poetry, Arabic American literature.)
  - undated, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:13:02); (Various poems celebrating Ramadan read by the authors Interviewee/Author/Reader: Daniel Abd Hayy Moore, Dasham Brookin, Um Ziad. Topics: poetry, Islam, Ramadan.)
  - Swimming Up the Tigris: Real Life Encounters with Iraq readings, undated
    - Chapter 3: Adnan in America
    - Chapter 6: There Goes the Medical System
    - Chapter 8: Books Break Sanctions
    - Chapter 21: Gravesites: Environmental Ruin in Iraq and Chapter 3: Adnan in America
    - Various readings
The Bentley Historical Library houses the following related collections: Radio Tahrir Web Archives and Radius of Arab-American Writers, Inc. records.
Additionally, a modified version of the metadata spreadsheet used to create this finding aid—and which contains further information about the bulk of the digital materials in this collection—can be found in this Deep Blue collection.